"The Best Milk Alternative: Oat vs. Soy Milk"
Plant-based milks
continue to expand their share
of the "milk" market.
Some see this shift
as a "palatable disruption,"
where people are encouraged
to care enough
about the environment,
health, and animal welfare
to adopt plant-based milks
but ultimately remain consumers
of a commodity food.
Do people even need
to consume milk,
whether plant-based or dairy?
Recent guidelines from
the Academy of Nutrition
and Dietetics
recommend that one-
to two-year-old children
consume whole cow's milk,
explicitly stating
that plant milks
should be avoided
with the exception of soy milk.
This triggered an outcry
in the medical community
with significant concerns
about dairy industry influence
and the lack of data showing
cow's milk offers any benefit
over plant-based milks
to young children.
Dr. Greger covered
this controversy in detail.
After weaning, milk of any kind
is not required and, in fact,
should not be relied upon
as a main source of calories.
Water is fine
provided it is combined
with a healthy, balanced diet.
U.S. federal nutrition policy
and dairy industry promotions
have long recognized
dairy milks
as a high-quality source
of protein and calcium.
However, although cow's milk
is rich in calcium,
it does not appear
to reduce bone fractures.
What's more,
consumption of cow's milk
carries its own risks
and must be compared against
risks of plant-based milks,
which are primarily
only problematic
when they are used
inappropriately
in otherwise unbalanced diets
that provide
inadequate solid foods.
Some milk products,
whether dairy or plant-based,
are fortified with vitamin D
or vitamin A.
Plant-based milk alternatives
could benefit from
nutrient density standards,
particularly
if individuals rely on them
as sources of protein
and calcium.
In a survey
of plant-based milk alternatives
in the U.S. market,
only soy milks served
as a "good" source of protein,
with around 7g per cup (240 ml)
and were consistently fortified.
Most other plant-based milks,
like almond, rice, coconut,
hemp, flaxseed,
and cashew "milks,"
are not great options
for toddlers and young children.
They have
inadequate nutrient profiles
to meet needs for protein,
calcium, and vitamin D.
Other fortified
plant-based milks,
like pea milk
and possibly oat milk,
might be more reasonable options
for young children
who need an alternative
to soy milk.
But not everyone agrees;
others recommend that other
fortified plant beverages,
like oat or almond milk,
are only okay
for older children.
Globally, soy milk has dominated
the plant-milk market,
making up more than 50%
of global plant-milk production.
But oat milk's popularity
continues to grow steadily,
outperforming others like
almond milk and coconut milk.
Oat milk came to the U.S. market
about 30 years ago,
but only recently,
with the arrival
of the Swedish brand Oatly
and its strategic
marketing campaign,
did oat milk
start overtaking soy milk
as the #2 plant-based milk
sold in the United States.
In Europe, oat milk has become
the #1 most widely-consumed
plant milk.
With more oat milk appearing
in refrigerator cases
at grocery stores,
how does it compare
to other plant milks,
particularly
NutritionFacts-recommended
unsweetened soy milk?
In terms of calcium
and vitamin D,
oat and soy milks have
similar amounts to cow's milk.
Soy surpasses oat
in terms of protein content,
and soy milk is generally lower
in added sugar,
but there is
considerable variation,
with unsweetened
and very sweetened options
on the market.
An important caveat to note
is that fortification
of plant-based milks
can differ by global region.
For example,
in the United States,
about 80% of plant-based milks
are fortified with vitamin D,
but only about 20%
are in Australia
and just 50% in Europe.
As some people rely on milk for
calcium and vitamin D sources,
this is your reminder to check
the nutrition labels,
whether for added sugar content
or fortification,
so you know exactly
what you are or are not getting.
What happens when you put oats
to the test for cholesterol?
People's LDL
can drop 10 points
from eating two small servings
of oatmeal a day
for eight weeks.
Oat-based cold cereals like
Cheerios appear to also work,
dropping LDL around 7 points
more than control
in the same time frame.
Does oat milk
have similar effects?
You don't know, until
it has been put to the test.
Oat milk versus soy milk
versus cow's milk.
People drank 3 to 4 cups
(720–960 ml) a day
of the respective milk
for 4 weeks,
and those who drank oat milk
or soy milk
had a significant drop in LDL,
around 8 points,
but drinking cow's milk
had no significant effect.
A slightly larger trial
of about 50 men
had similar results
for oat milk,
an 8-point drop in LDL
over 5 weeks
for those drinking 3 cups
(720 ml) of oat milk per day,
versus no effect
in the control group
drinking rice milk.
So, 3 cups of oat milk
has similar effects
on LDL cholesterol
as a cup and a half (360 ml)
of cooked oatmeal.
Some of these
cholesterol-lowering effects
may be due to
the beta-glucan fiber in oats.
Oats are one of the few foods,
because of their
beta-glucan content,
that can have a "health claim"
for lowering heart disease risk
put on their packaging.
But the soy protein
in soy milk can, too.
And soy milk has more than
10 times the polyphenol content
of oat milk.
Polyphenol-rich diets
have been associated
with a reduced risk
of chronic diseases,
like heart disease,
some cancers,
and Type 2 diabetes,
yet another reason
it is the healthier choice.